Guide to the Nell Irvin Painter Papers, 1793-2021 and undated, bulk 1876-2007 RL.00990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nell Irvin Painter papers
1793-2021 and undated, bulk 1876-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Painter, Nell Irvin
RL.00990
186.5 Linear Feet
Nell Irvin Painter is a scholar, teacher, and writer in 19th- and 20th-century American and African American history who has been a faculty member of Harvard, Princeton, and the Universities of North Carolina and Pennsylvania. Collection spans the years 1793-2019, with the bulk of the material dating between 1876 and 2007, and contains correspondence, research notes, photocopies of original documents, manuscripts, publication proofs, syllabi, department memoranda, records of her speaking engagements, photographs, personal journals, papers, and photographs, many varying audiovisual formats, and computer diskettes. Also contains extensive file series related to the research and writing of five of her major books: Exodusters: Black Migration to Kansas after Reconstruction; The Narrative of Hosea Hudson: His Life as a Negro Communist in the South; Standing at Armageddon: The United States, 1877-1919; Sojourner Truth, A Life, A Symbol; and Creating Black Americans: African-American History and its Meanings, 1619 to the Present.
Access Restrictions
Access is restricted. Restrictions are outlined in the Collection Control File. Unprocessed additions are closed until processing.
Provenance
The Nell Irvin Painter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002-2022.
Biographical Note
1942 Aug. 2 Born Nell Elizabeth Irvin, in Houston, Texas, to Frank and Dona L. Irvin
1962-1963 Studied French medieval history at University of Bordeaux, France
1964 B.A. (honors) in anthropology, University of California, Berkeley
1965-1966 Studied at University of Ghana, Institute of African Studies; met Colin Painter, a linguistics teacher at the university, to whom she was married from 1965 to 1966
1967 M.A. in African history, University of California, Los Angeles
1969 Entered Harvard doctoral program in history; met Nellie Y. McKay, a first-year graduate student in English, and began lifelong friendship
1974 Ph.D. in American history, Harvard University
1974-1977 Assistant Professor of History, University of Pennsylvania
1976 Published Exodusters: Black Migration to Kansas After Reconstruction
1977-1980 Associate Professor of History, University of Pennsylvania
1979 Published The Narrative of Hosea Hudson: His Life as a Negro Communist in the South
1980-1988 Professor of History, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
1982-1983 Guggenheim Fellow
1985-1986 Russell Sage Visiting Professor of History, Hunter College of the City University of New York
1987 Published Standing at Armageddon: The United States, 1877-1919
1988-1989 Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences Fellow
1988-1991 Professor of History, Princeton University
1989 Oct. 14 Married Glenn R. Shafer, a professor in the business school of the University of Kansas
1990-1991 Acting Director, Program in Afro-American Studies, Princeton University
1991- Edwards Professor of American History, Princeton University
1992-1993 National Endowment for the Humanities Fellowship
1996 Published Sojourner Truth, A Life, A Symbol
1997-2000 Director, Program in African American Studies, Princeton University
2002 Published Southern History Across the Color Line
2004 Apr. Retirement conference in her honor, Princeton University: "Constructing the Past, Creating the Future: The Legacy of Nell Irvin Painter"
2005 Published Creating Black Americans: African American History and Its Meanings, 1619 to the Present
2005 Received Emeritus Status at Princeton University
2007 Fellow, American Academy of Arts and Sciences
2010 Published The History of White People
In addition to items listed in the chronology, Painter has been an active member of a wide variety of professional organizations, including: the American Antiquarian Society, the American Historical Association, the American Studies Association, Association of Black Women Historians, Berkshire Conference of Women Historians, the Institute for Southern Studies, the National Book Foundation, Organization of American Historians, and the Southern Historical Association. She has also served on the editorial boards of several publishers and journals, including the University of North Carolina Press, the Encyclopedia of American Cultural and Intellectual History, and SIGNS.
Sources for biographical information include: Contemporary Authors Online; Contemporary Black Biography; Notable Black American Women; Who's Who in America, 2005-; and Painter's web site, www.nellpainter.com.
Collection Overview
The Nell Irvin Painter Papers span the years 1793-2021, with the bulk of the material dating between 1876 and 2007, and are primarily composed of the extensive correspondence, writing, research, teaching materials, and other professional papers that Painter has produced in her long career as a scholar, teacher, and writer in 19th- and 20th-century American and African American history. The materials document the breadth and depth of Painter's interests and her intellectual and personal influence on a generation of historians. Her varied roles as student, teacher, colleague, and mentor are recorded in a wide variety of formats: correspondence with colleagues, students, family, and friends; syllabi, department memoranda, and meeting minutes from her graduate and faculty positions at Harvard, Princeton, and the Universities of North Carolina and Pennsylvania; materials from many professional organizations in the fields of African American history, Southern history, American studies, and women's studies; and records of her speaking engagements, conferences, and meetings. Painter the historian and author are revealed in the extensive notes, photocopies, recordings, photographs, manuscripts, and proofs produced in writing many articles and five of her major books: Exodusters: Black Migration to Kansas after Reconstruction; The Narrative of Hosea Hudson: His Life as a Negro Communist in the South; Standing at Armageddon: The United States, 1877-1919; Sojourner Truth, A Life, A Symbol; and Creating Black Americans: African-American History and its Meanings, 1619 to the Present. The portrait is rounded out by the materials in other series: personal files, which include materials from her student years at Harvard and abroad in Ghana and France as well as personal journals; a few papers of Ghanaian writer Ayi Kwei Armah; photographs, including many historical photographs of African Americans as well as many personal snapshots in color and black-and-white; and other non-print media such as audiotapes, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and computer diskettes.
Painter's research files contain a wealth of information about many topics in American history: biography of African Americans; biography as a literary form; slavery; Reconstruction; the 1870s migration from the South to Kansas; a variety of social reform movements--such as abolition, communism, labor, and women's suffrage--and movers, such as Sojourner Truth and Hosea Hudson; and the history of social conditions and political change in the United States from the early-19th to the mid-20th century, particularly as expressed in race relations, in women's history, and in the South. At the same time, Painter's papers also constitute a contemporary record of many trends in American culture such as career and educational choices and opportunities for academic women and African American professionals. Her correspondence with students, colleagues, and longtime friends such as Nellie Y. McKay, her teaching material and academic files, her papers from an array of historians' organizations, and her personal journals each shed their own light on these themes.
The collection is arranged in these series: Correspondence, Writings and Research, Teaching Materials, Professional Service, Personal Files, Photographic Materials, Audiovisual Materials, Electronic Formats, and a collection of private papers collected by Painter, the Ayi Kwei Armah Papers. The first four series comprise almost eighty percent of the physical extent of the collection and are each divided into several subseries. The Correspondence Series follows Painter's personal life, education, and professional career from her graduate years at Harvard in the late 1960s through her retirement from Princeton in 2004.
The Writings and Research Series is arranged in seven subseries, the first five of which are based on five of Painter's major books; the final two subseries are Other Research Topics, which gathers many of Painter's shorter writings, and Writings by Others. With the exception of the last, all the subseries here contain correspondence with colleagues and editors; typescript drafts of works; various stages of proof; extensive photocopies of archival materials and published articles; voluminous notes about her readings and research; and some photographs and recordings, most of which have been removed to their respective series for preservation.
The Teaching Materials Series documents Painter's work with students and academic colleagues at Harvard, the University of Pennsylvania, the University of North Carolina, Hunter College, and Princeton University. It is arranged into two series: Courses Subseries, with syllabi, reading lists, and Painter's notes on the development of her courses that reflect the evolution of women's studies and African American studies in the curriculum; and the Academic Files Subseries, revealing Painter's many different roles over three decades: graduate student, job applicant, junior and tenured faculty member, dissertation advisor, mentor, and department head.
The Professional Service Series, arranged in two subseries, documents Painter's activities in the broader academic community beyond her university of employment and her personal connections through materials from well over one hundred professional organizations, conferences, foundations, committees and task forces, as well as editorial boards of journals and publishers with which Painter has worked during her career. The Engagements Subseries gathers documents relating to addresses, speeches, and awards ceremonies at some three hundred conferences, meetings, and symposia.
Five smaller series and a gathering of oversize material round out the collection. The Personal Files Series contains an assortment of records such as curriculum vitae; documents about her family; and some records of her student years, especially her travel and study in France and Africa. The series includes some three dozen personal journals covering most of the years from 1959-2005 containing entries about her life and career (NOTE: some journals are CLOSED to use; see details in the series note). The Photographic Materials Series contains several hundred photographs, negatives, and slides, predominantly personal and travel snapshots but also including professional portraits of Painter as well as a number of original photographs and reproductions of archival photographs she used in her research and writing. Much of the material in the early years of the Audiovisual Materials Series is related to her research and writing; by the 1990s, the content shifts focus to documenting Painter herself on the occasion of various interviews and addresses. The Electronic Formats Series consists of diskettes containing correspondence and drafts of writings. The Oversize Materials contains items from several series and subseries are gathered. The final series in the collection consists not of Painter's own work but that of a Ghanaian novelist and poet; see the Ayi Kwei Armah Papers (RESTRICTED) series note for further information on the provenance and usage of these materials.
Unprocessed additions to the collection are listed at the end of the collection guide.
Note about date range of materials: The primary material produced by Painter begins around 1959 with her earliest journals. Earlier dates in various series, occurring mainly in Writings and Research, reflect the intellectual content and original publication of the large volume of reproduced research material present in the collection.
Related Material
The following collections in the Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript and Special Collections Library may contain related material:
Darlene Clark Hine Papers, circa 1879-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1996Irvin family Papers, circa 1890s-2003 Nell Irvin Painter Letters and Photographs, 1957-2004 (provenance: Jacqueline Bryant Smith)Nellie Y. McKay Papers [CLOSED: unprocessed collection]
In addition, Painter's interview tapes with Hosea Hudson are housed in the Southern Historical Collection at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. For further information, see the subseries note for the Hosea Hudson Subseries in the Writings and Research Series.
Conditions Governing Access
Unprocessed additions are restricted and must be screened before access by patrons.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials in this collection are fragile audiovisual formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials in this collection are electronic records that may need to be reformatted. Access copies of electronic records require special equipment. Contact Research Services for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note: Personal journals are closed to research for 50 years from the date of creation.
Migration, Internal -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Reconstruction; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877); Videocassettes; African Americans -- Study and teaching; African fiction -- 20th century; Biography as a literary form; College teachers -- Correspondence; Female friendship; Feminist theory; Historians -- United States; History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; United States -- History -- 1865-1921; United States -- History -- Textbooks; United States -- Race relations; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1933; Women -- Suffrage -- United States -- History; Women -- Southern States -- History -- 19th century; Ghana -- In literature; Women -- United States -- History; Ghana -- Description and travel; Southern States -- History -- Study and teaching; Audiocassettes; France -- Description and travel; United States -- History -- Study and teaching; United States -- Social conditions -- 1865-1918; Southern States -- Historiography; Kansas -- History; African Americans -- Biography; African Americans -- Education (Higher); African Americans -- Employment; African Americans -- History -- 1877-1964; African Americans -- Professional education; Abolitionists -- United States; African American college teachers; African American women -- Education (Higher); African Americans -- Photography; Scholars -- Correspondence; Slavery -- United States; Social reformers -- United States; African Americans -- History -- 19th century; African Americans -- Historiography; African Americans -- Intellectual life; African Americans -- Migrations -- History -- 19th century; Machine-readable records; Photographs; Journals; Proofs (printed matter); Audiotapes; University of Pennsylvania -- Faculty; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Faculty; Truth, Sojourner, 1799-1883; Princeton University -- Faculty; Painter, Nell Irvin; McKay, Nellie Y.; Hudson, Hosea; Harvard University -- Students; Armah, Ayi Kwei, 1939-
- Correspondence Series, 1862-2008 and undated, bulk 1970-2007, 98 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains professional correspondence between Painter and her professors, colleagues, and students over the course of her career; personal letters to and from family, friends, and colleagues; and some administrative and interdepartmental memoranda from each of the universities at which Painter served as professor. Documents Painter's personal life, education, and career from her graduate years at Harvard in the late 1960s up through her retirement from Princeton in 2004. Major figures who corresponded with Painter include African-American novelist Toni Morrison; professors of English Houston A. Baker, Jr., Werner Sollors, and Nellie Y. McKay; and historians Darlene Clark Hine and William L. Andrews. Theirs and others' correspondence may appear in either the Chronological Subseries or Alphabetical Subseries. Professional correspondence also includes some letters related to editorial matters, organizations such as the National Endowment for the Humanities, and such publishers as Heinneman of the African Writer's Series. Arranged in four subseries: the Chronological, Alphabetical, Student/Candidate Files, and Nellie Y. McKay (CLOSED).
  Materials Retrieval Note: In addition to the material gathered in this series, Painter's extensive correspondence can be found in many other places in the collection. This is particularly true of the Writings and Research Series and the Professional Service Series. In the case of the former, each of the five subseries for Painter's major books contains a Correspondence subgroup within it related to research and publication of the book, and correspondence also appears in various folders throughout the other two subseries. In the Professional Service Series, correspondence appears in both subseries--Organizations and Engagements--though more substantially in the former. Thus in order to be sure of seeing all correspondence that might relate to a particular book, for example, patrons should retrieve not only the correspondence from that book's subseries in the Writings and Research Series, but also any boxes in the Correspondence Series that originate from any applicable time spans or persons in the Chronological and Alphabetical subseries, respectively.
  - Chronological Subseries, 1957-2008 and undated, bulk 1970-2007, 60 boxes
    Correspondence between Painter and professors, colleagues, students, friends, and family over the course of her career.
    Arranged in chronological order by year, month, and, in some places, day. Where possible, Painter's own system of labeling has been retained, which accounts for some overlap in dates across folders. Materials from the mid to late 1990s and early 2000 often have been divided into the categories professional, business, and personal as Painter saw fit, and the folders containing these materials have been so labeled along with the year and, at times, month. Printed electronic correspondence was largely separated by Painter from traditionally-formatted letters when it first began to appear in the mid-1990s and has been retained in her folders; after a few years, however, she began to treat e-mail as any other correspondence and by 2002 was interfiling items regardless of how they originated.
    Processing and retrieval note for 2008 and 2010 accessions: There have been two substantial expansions of this subseries since the collection was originally processed in 2006. Materials from Accession 2008-0016 were integrated into the subseries chronologically but not physically, meaning that newer box numbers will sometimes appear out of strict numerical sequence. Materials from Accession 2010-0116 were processed minimally, and can be found appended at the end of this inventory. Researchers are advised to examine all these points when seeking to retrieve all correspondence from a particular period of time, especially materials dated 1997 or later.
    - 1957-1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969 Apr.-Dec. (Box 1)
    - 1970 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970 Autumn (Box 1)
    - 1971 Jan-Dec., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1972 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1973 Jan.-June (Box 1)
    - 1973 Jul.-Dec. (Box 2)
    - 1974 Jan.-Dec., 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1975 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1976 Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 Spring (Box 2)
    - 1976 Autumn-1977 Spring, outgoing, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1977 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1977, Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1978, Last minute correspondence, Robinson Hall, etc. (Box 3)
    - 1978 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1978 Feb.-Aug., Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979-1980, Historical, general (Box 4)
    - Undated, circa 1970-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1979-1980, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 1980 Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1980 Mar.-Oct., Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 1981 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1981 Sept.-Dec., Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - 1982 Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1982 Jan.-Dec., Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1983 Jan.-Dec., 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1983 Autumn, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1983-1984, Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - 1984 Spring, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1984 Autumn, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1985 (Box 7)
      - Spring, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - June-Aug., Letters received, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Aug.-Sept., Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Sept.-Dec., Folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 7)
      - Sept.-Dec., Folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 1986
      - Jan.-Feb., 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Mar.-May, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Summer, Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - Autumn, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Autumn, Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 10)
    - 1987
      - Mar.-Dec., 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Spring, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Spring, Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - June, Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - July, Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - Autumn, Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - Late autumn, Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - 1987 Dec.- 1988 Spring (Box 12)
    - 1988
      - Feb.-Dec. (Box 12)
      - Spring, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Spring, Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Summer, Miscellaneous, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 12)
      - Summer, Miscellaneous, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 13)
      - Sept.-Nov., Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Winter, Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1989
      - Jan.-Dec., Folder 1 of 3 (Box 13)
      - Jan.-Dec., Folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 14)
      - Jan.-Dec., Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Jan.-May, Miscellaneous, Folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 14)
      - Jan.-May, Miscellaneous, Folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 15)
      - Summer, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Undated, circa 1980-1989, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - 1989-1990, Folders 1-4 of 6 (Box 15)
    - 1989-1990, Folders 5-6 of 6 (Box 16)
    - 1989-1990, Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1990
      - Jan.-Oct. (Box 16)
      - Mar.-May (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Summer, Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - Autumn, Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Aug.-Oct., Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - Oct.-Dec., Miscellaneous (Box 18)
      - Dec. (Box 18)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 18)
    - 1990-1991, Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1991
      - Jan. (Box 18)
      - Mar.-Dec. (Box 18)
      - Mar., Miscellaneous (Box 18)
      - Spring, History Miscellaneous, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 18)
      - Spring, History Miscellaneous, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 19)
      - Jan.-Dec., Personal (Box 19)
      - June-Aug., History, 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Tasks from June (Box 19)
      - Oct.-Dec., 5 folders (Box 19)
      - June-Dec., Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 20)
    - 1991-1992, Professional (Box 20)
    - 1991 Dec.-1992 Jan., 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 1992
      - Jan.-Feb., 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Feb.-May., 5 folders (Box 21)
      - Spring, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - June-Dec., 4 folders (Box 21)
      - May-Dec., Professional, 10 folders (Box 22)
      - General (Box 22)
    - 1992 Fall-1993 Feb., E-mail (Box 23)
    - 1993
      - Jan.-Sep., 9 folders (Box 23)
      - Oct.-Dec., 5 folders (Box 24)